Guide to the Rothschild's Department Store records, 1866-1957
Rothschild's Department Store records, 1866-2957
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Rothschild's Department Store Records, 1866-1957
3846
Rothschild's Department Store
3.7 cubic ft.
Ledgers, account books, legal documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes ledgers and account books (1914-1935) of customer orders and dealer invoices. The volumes dealing with customers frequently record the customers' tableware patterns and prices. Also, deeds and title abstracts and searches (1866-1957) for various properties in the city of Ithaca and two appraisals (1923-1933) of the Rothschild Brothers Building.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Rothschild's Department Store was a family business founded in 1882 as the Boston Variety Store by Jacob Rothschild. His brother Daniel joined him in 1884. Six years later another brother, Isaac, joined the firm, which then became known as Rothschild Brothers. The business was sold in 1980.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes ledgers and account books (1914-1935) of customer orders and dealer invoices for china, glass, silver and other tableware, kitchenware, toys and games. The volumes dealing with customers, including individuals, churches, educational institutions, fraternities, hospitals, restaurants, and hotels in Ithaca, New York and nationwide, frequently record the customers' tableware patterns and prices; one volume pertains to orders for Statler hotels and restaurants. Also, deeds and title abstracts and searches (1866-1957) for various properties in the city of Ithaca, particularly the area which is now the Ithaca Commons, and two appraisals (1923-1933) of the Rothschild Brothers Building.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Rothschild's Department Store (Ithaca, N.Y).; Rothschild, Daniel.; Rothschild, Isaac.; Rothschild, Jacob.
Subjects:
Department stores.; Stores, Retail.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- China customer orders, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Dealer invoices, tableware, cookware, clocks, etc., 1919-1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- G-Z; customers, mostly businesses and fraternities; tableware, kitchenware, etc., 1922-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Le-Pe; customers outside Ithaca: churches, hotels, restaurants, hospitals, 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Pi-S (same as Volume 4), 1923-1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- T-Z (same as Volume 4 and 5), 1923-1927 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Dealer invoices, tableware, misc., 1926, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Fine China; customers, patterns and prices, ca. 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Dealer invoices, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Outside (not Ithaca) customers; hotels, restaurants, country clubs, colleges, hospitals; tableware, misc., ca. 1928-1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Local, mostly Cornell University fraternities, dining halls, restaurants, tableware, misc. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Dealer invoices, mostly toys and games, 1930-1931 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Statler Hotels and Restaurants; tableware, 1930-1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Appraisal for Rothschild Brothers' buildings, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Appraisal for Leon D. Rothschild: East State Street properties, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- (Loose material from Volume 5: correspondence and price lists) (Box 5, Folder 1)
- #1 Deeds and Abstracts of Title of Property, 155 E State St. and 110 N Tioga St., 1866-1913; Lots 62 and 63: Miles Finch, Henry L. Wilgus, Helen M. Tolfree, Sarah F. Tolfree, Sarah E. Wilgus, Peter Fish, Horace I. Smith, Jacob, Daniel and Isaac Rothschild (Box 5, Folder 2)
- #2 Journal Block on Tioga St and also residence on Buffalo St. "Deeds and Abstracts of Titles of S Tioga St building":, 1886-1913; Lots 62 and 63, 1886-1913: Fenis Finch, Miles Finch, Henry L. Wilgus, Clarissa M. Selkreg, Peter Fish, Douglas Boardman, John H. Selkreg, ADW Bruyn (?), Andrew J. Miller, Helen M. Tolfree [nee Miller], Charles S. Tourlellat, Sarah T. Tourtellat [nee Miller], Horace I. Smith, Sarah Ross, O. B. Curran and wife, Clarence L. Smith, F. C. Cornell, James Ross, Harriet E. Ross, U.S. Express Co., Alethea T. Apgar, Charles S. Miles, Alfred Wells, John Carr, Charles W. Swift, Jacob and Rebecca Rothschild, Isaac and Daniel Rothschild, William Andrus, William A. Church, Fannie S. Rothschild [wife of Isaac], Rothschild Brothers, Inc. (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
- #4 Weed Property, Deed, Abstract of Title, Discharged Mortgage, Certificate of Discharge, Search of Green St. and Tioga St. Property., 1888-1954; Amy D. Barber, Louise K. Weed, John Gauntlett and wife, William Andrus, George McChain, Frederick Andrus, William A. Church, Marcus C. and Alice V. Niver, Joseph and Amelia La Point, Harriet E. Webster, Benjamin Gould, Lena F. Weed Potter, Charles B. Potter, Hoffman C. Steinberg, Rothschild Brothers, Inc., Jacob Rothschild, Catherine G. Comes, James Macera and wife. (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
- #6 Deed and Abstract of Title, Cornell Building, S. Tioga St., 1923, 1924; Eunice Cornell Taylor, Franklin C. Cornell, Cordelia H. and Dorothy Cornell, Carl Schallowitz, Henry L. Wilgus, Rothschild Brothers, Jacob Rothschild (Box 5, Folder 7)
- #7 Papers Pertaining to Henry L. Wilgus, Wilgus Block, lots 62 and 63., 1870-1911; Henry L. Wilgus and wife, Peter Fish, Horace I. Smith, Jacob, Isaac and Daniel H. Rothschild, Rothschild Brothers, Clarissa M. Selkreg, Miles Finch, Louisa J. Sprague, [Dr. William D. E. Marsh, Dr. Tinker, Business men's Association, Conservatory of Music - tenants], Helen M. Tolfree, David Roe, Sarah E. Wilgus, Mynderse Van Cleef. (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
- "Deed, Abstract of Title and Papers pertaining to Property, 130-132 E State St and 117 E Seneca St", 1899-1949; Quigg Block, lot 41 1899-1949. James Quigg, Rothschild Brothers, George West, Arthur P. Brooks, Julia A. Quigg, Daniel, Jacob and Isaac Rothschild, Franklin Atwater and wife Harriet O., John W. Quigg, Albert A. Stannard, Mary Hilton, Emeline Quigg, H.J. Bool Co., J. Lakin Baldridge, Jess J. Dall, Jr. and wife Constance G., Fred A. Rogalsky and wife Dorothy C., Leon D. Rothschild, James N. Rothschild, Nancy Rothschild [Deutsch], Francis M. Willis, Hattie L. Hill, Le Roy D. Neish and wife Blanchard L., Harold P. Denniston, Muriel J. Denniston, Rhonda N. Rothschild. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Legal document. "121 E Seneca St Corp April 1957" [formerly premises of Oriental Hotel, Tioga Hotel, 130 S. Tioga St.]., 1957; Venera Macera, Vincenzo Macera, Fraternal Order of Eagles, James N. Rothschild. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Loose papers:, Junior Republic Inn Company shares, Daniel Rothschild; documents related to those in folder 5; meeting notice--directors of Rothschild Brothers; release: Benjamin E. Green, Abbie E. Green, Florence E. Green to Rothschild Brothers. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- 2 photographs of Rothschild's Department Store, ca. 1957 (Box 4)
- 1 photograph of James and Leon Rothschild, man, 1951 (Box 4)
- 2 sale catalogs, 1905 and ca. 1922 (Box 4)
- 1 invitation to opening of new store, 1915 (Box 4)
- 1 copy magazine, Sound Selling, 1956 (Box 4)